A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Officers, RG 3 FA1797
Rockefeller Archive Center
John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Officers, RG 3
1931-2017
Rockefeller Archive Center
John S. and James L. Knight Foundation
FA1797
13.98 Cubic Feet (39 containers)
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
Record Group 3 documents the work of the Foundation's officers through their correspondence and subject files, speeches and writings. It contains files for presidents Creed Black, C.C. Gibson, Ben Maidenburg and Hodding Carter; treasurers Charles Clark and DavidCatrow; chief program officers James Spaniolo and Penelope McPhee; chief financial officer Timothy Crowe; and co-founders John and James Knight. The papers of Chairman of the Board Lee Hills are particularly important to this record group. They contain a complete record of the Foundation's activities and issues during the years 1968 to the early 1990s. Most Foundation records dating before the move to Miami in 1990 exist only on microfiche, or in Lee Hills' papers.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged as follows:
Subgroup 1: Correspondence and Subject Files, 1931-2017
Subgroup 2: Speeches and Writings, 1958-2017
- Correspondence and Subject Files, 1931-2017; 1; 12.65 Cubic Feet 35 containers
  - Black, Creed, 1971-1999; 1.1; 2.37 Cubic Feet 6 containers
    Scope and Contents
    Creed C. Black, President, 1987-1998. Mr. Black's papers are contained in six letter size boxes. One box of files records the National Community Development Initiative, Strategic Planning, the Cities Program, and the Symphony Initiative. There are also files on legal issues, including a memo and reference materials from Lee Hills to the Trustees in 1982 on Conflicts of Interest; guidance for Trustees and Advisors on distributing grants (1988); and correspondence on the relationship between Knight Foundation and Knight-Ridder (1991). One box refers to the relocation of Knight Foundation offices from Akron to Miami. Mr. Black's correspondence can also be found in the files on the Knight Commission for Intercollegiate Athletics (SEE Record Group 6), the National Community Development Initiative and the Cities Program (SEE Record Group 5, Community Initiatives), the Journalism Program (SEE Record Group 5, Journalism), and in Board of Trustees files (SEE Record Group 1, Board of Trustees).
    - Journalism Program, 1971 August 5-1982 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General
      Knight File Number - 1569
      Correspondence regarding the Journalism Program and committee leadership, program development and journalism education.
    - Cities Program Correspondence, 1975 August 1-1989 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 1015
      Correspondence regarding the Cities Program from 1975-1989, including its background and history, planning, guidelines, notes on meetings. Includes Confidential Guidelines for Internal Use, prepared by the board and endorsed by James L. Knight.
    - Governance Issues, 1978 April 26-1987 November 9 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 1601
      Correspondence re: governance issues such as Articles of Incorporation, meetings, elections, and titles. The Distribution Committee is discussed.
    - Indemnification, 1978 July 19-1987 November 17 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 1605
      Legal correspondence from Baker & Hostetler and Brouse & McDowell on the indemnification of trustees, including signed agreements for indemnification by trustees, 1987.
    - Akron Area Foundations Group, 1979 July 13-1992 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 1574
      Correspondence regarding Knight Foundation's participation in the Akron Area Foundations Group, 1979-1992.
    - Policy--White Paper, 1980 January 24-1980 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 1561
      Correspondence, meeting agenda and minutes of the policy meeting on the Foundation's White Paper.
    - Gannett Foundation, 1981 August 25-1982 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 1606
      Correspondence re: Knight Foundation's growth and direction from the Gannett Foundation.
    - Beacon Journal Fund, 1982 June 21-July 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 1573
      Correspondence regarding self-dealing and the Beacon Journal Fund, 1982.
    - Legal Issues: Conflict of Interest, 1982 January 6-1988 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 771
      Letter from Lee Hills to the Board of Trustees regarding the issue of Conflicts of Interest, and an accompanying section from a book on the subject. C.C. Gibson sent these materials to Creed Black to read on 1/25/1988.
    - John S. Knight Papers at the University of Akron, 1984 November 26-1999 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 1535
      Correspondence re: the John S. Knight Papers at the University of Akron. Includes a copy of John S. Knight's will, and a report from the Winthrop Group on the condition and status of the processing of the papers for the archive at the University.
    - John S. Knight Estate, 1981 June 19-1986 January 30 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 1536
      Correspondence and legal memos regarding the John S. Knight Estate and its bequest to Knight Foundation, 1981-1986.
    - Knight-Ridder Broadcasting, 1986 March 5-1989 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 1572
      Correspondence regarding making grants to Knight-Ridder broadcasting cities, 1986-1989.
    - Consortium for the Advancement for Private Higher Education (CAPHE), 1988 July 13-1992 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 1570
      Correspondence regarding Knight Foundation's relationship with CAPHE, the Consortium for the Advancement for Private Higher Education, 1988-1992.
    - Cities Program Correspondence, 1988, 1988 July 8 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 1018
      Cities Program: memo from James L. Knight to KF Associates regarding guidelines for the program, and his comments on the guidelines, 7/8/88.
    - Cities Program Proposal Evaluation, 1988 July 6-September 8 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Knight File Number - 1603
      Correspondence re: the Cities Program proposal evaluation process, and procedures used by Associates in KF cities.
    - Education Program, 1988 October 4 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 1553
      Overview of the Education Program for the support of liberal arts colleges, 1988.
    - Fort Howard Paper, 1988 August 16-December 14 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 3885
      Correspondence and settlement agreement re: Fort Howard Paper's failure to accept KF's tender on a timely basis, which resulted in a loss of investment funds by KF.
    - Grant Evaluation, 1988 December 8-1990 November 30 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 1567
      Correspondence and memos procedures for evaluating grants and methods for making more effective grants. File included a proposal for evaluation methods by Evaluation and Research Associates.
    - Job Descriptions for Knight Foundation staff, 1988 January 6-8 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 3888
      Memos to Creed Black from KF staffers with descriptions of their jobs.
    - Journalism Program, 1988 March 31-1993 January 4 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 1554
      Correspondence re: staffing of the Journalism program and the creation of a Journalism Advisory Committee.
    - Legal Issues: Grant Distribution, 1988 June 20 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 772
      Correspondence and a report to Knight Foundation from Brouse & McDowell giving guidance to trustees and advisers on distributing grants.
    - Legal Issues: IRS rulings, taxes, governance, 1986 August 11-1991 January 4 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 1571
      Correspondence with Brouse & McDowell regarding legal issues such as IRS rulings, taxes and governance, 1986-1991.
    - Chandler, Carolyn, 1989 December 26-1990 March 7 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 1831
      Consultant agreement, proposal for developing white paper on literacy, etc.
    - Cities Program, 1989 December 19 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 1017
      Cities Program: memo on background of the guidelines for the program written by Sarah Wright, 12/19/89.
    - Grant Applicants, 1989 July 20 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 773
      Memo from Sarah Wright to Creed Black regarding her discussion with John Edie (tax advisor?) re. recommendations for determining the tax exempt status of grant applicants.
    - Knight-Ridder, Inc., 1988 July 6-1991 May 22 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 3892
      Memos re: general KF issues including personnel changes and the separation of Knight-Ridder and KF. Also included is a memo from Creed Black to KF Associates (which includes a covering memo by James Knight) about revised guidelines for giving.
    - Cities Program, 1990 January 2-March 16 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 1016
      Cities Program memos and correspondence regarding guidelines, planning program in San Jose, 1990.
    - Programmatic Aspects of Donor Advised Fund Pilot Program, 1990 February 27 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 2643
      Memo from Sarah Wright states the original program intent of donor advised funds in community foundations, provides background information, results of the pilot program, and observations and recommendations. Appendix A: Grant Guidelines, and Appendix C: Community Foundations Memo, 1987, are included.
    - Florida Funders Group, 1990 March 15-1991 August 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 3894
      Correspondence inviting KF to join a loose affiliation of funders based in Florida and, later, the decision to merge the group with the Donors Forum of Florida.
    - IRS Tax Determination, 1990 October 22-1991 February 22 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Knight File Number - 1393
      Corres. from Brouse & McDowell re. IRS Tax Determination, including copy of 1951 ruling that KF does not have to file an income tax return (because KF was organized for educational purposes). Also includes application for registration of fictitious name, corres. and certification concerning KF authorization to transact business in the State of Florida.
    - Knight Foundation Associates: Cities Program, 1990 March 2 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Knight File Number - 774
      Memo from Creed Black to Knight Foundation Associates regarding effective uses of Cities Program money.
    - Donors Forum of Miami, 1990 August 17-24 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Knight File Number - 1577
      Correspondence with Donors Forum of Miami regarding the move to Miami and Knight Foundation's participation in Donors Forum.
    - Gannett Foundation, 1990 July 30 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Knight File Number - 1576
      Memo from Creed Black to Lee Hills regarding the Gannett Foundation, and a comparison of expenditures between Gannett and Knight Foundation.
    - National Community Development Initiative (NCDI), 1990 October 18-November 26 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Knight File Number - 1565
      Correspondence regarding the development of NCDI (National Community Development Initiative) and Knight Foundation's participation in the program.
    - Relocation to Miami, 1990 May 19-December 14 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Knight File Number - 1575
      Correspondence regarding Knight Foundation's relocation to Miami, including reimbursement policies, expenses, and news coverage of the move to Miami.
    - The Enterprise Foundation, 1991 June 7-July 30 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Knight File Number - 1568
      Correspondence regarding program related investments and the DBA program in Miami (programs through the Enterprise Foundation).
    - Grant Cycle, 1991 December 12 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Knight File Number - 1552
      Memo from Penny McPhee to staff and trustees re: the possibility of having a six-month grant cycle, 1991.
    - Knight-Ridder and Knight Foundation Relationship, 1991 June 12-28 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Knight File Number - 775
      Statement and memos by Creed Black to Knight Foundation Associates regarding the role of the Foundation, its relationship to Knight-Ridder, and the significant difference between the two. Includes responses from associates in Knight-Ridder cities.
    - Lexington Herald-Leader, 1991 February 19-September 23 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Knight File Number - 3895
      Letters from Creed Black re: KF grant in honor or Lexington Herald-Leader publisher, John Carroll.
    - Strategic Planning, 1991 February 19-August 29 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      Knight File Number - 1563
      Correspondence with Arthur Raybin & Associates and Knight Foundation staff re: creating a strategic plan.
    - Strategic Planning Retreat Materials, 1991 June 20-22 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      Knight File Number - 1154
      Materials from the Strategic Planning Retreat (flip charts, summaries of discussions) held on 6/20-22/91 on Key Biscayne, FL.
    - Strategic Planning Meeting with Associates: Addendum I, 1991 October 4 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      Knight File Number - 1019
      "Sharpen the Focus--Heighten the Impact" Strategic Planning meeting with associates, addendum one, 10/4/91. Includes an essay by Alan J. Pifer on the basic nature of foundations, a journalism program description, planning statement on education, arts & culture program description, Wall Street Journal article on Community Development Corporations (CDCs), and a statement of the co-chairs of Knight Foundation Commission on Inter-Collegiate Athletics.
    - James L. Knight Estate, 1981 March 16-1995 June 14 (Box 3, Folder 1-9)
      Knight File Number - 1608
      Correspondence and legal papers re: the James L. Knight Estate, including the bequest to Knight Foundation, disbursements and tax issues. Also includes James L. Knight's estate plan, investment considerations report for the Finance Committee, correspondence on attorney fees and grant spending planning. 9 folders.
    - Lee Hills Hall, University of Missouri, 1992 April 24 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 1840
      C. Black corres. with Dean Miller concerning the "Missouri" (school newspaper).
    - Hurricane Andrew, 1992 September 4-29 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 1556
      Correspondence regarding spending, relief for staff members and other foundations' efforts for rebuilding following Hurricane Andrew, 1992. Also included is a hand-written thank you note from Elizabeth Dole to Creed Black thanking him for the Foundation's donation to the Salvation Army Disaster Relief Fund.
    - Grant Evaluation, 1992 September 15 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 1832
      Memo from Linda Raybin and background materials. Includes Sarah Wright's overview of Knight Foundations evaluation process (1990), recommendations from the Council on Foundations and an excerpt from the Council's book on evaluation, and excerpts from handbooks on evaluation from the Coca Cola Foundation and the Kellogg Foundation.
    - Council on Foundations, 1993 March 25 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 1591
      Letters from Knight Foundation staff about experiences with the Council on Foundations, written to decide on whether or not to renew KF's membership.
    - Minority Journalism Handbook, 1993 April 14 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 1551
      Memo from Scott McGehee and Jim Spaniolo suggesting the publication of a Minority Journalism Handbook to the Journalism Advisory Committee, 1993.
    - Performing Arts Center, 1993 May 25-1995 January 26 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 1587
      Correspondence regarding the possibility of making a grant to fund the Performing Arts Center in Miami, and the question of self dealing.
    - Legal Issues--Reincorporation in Florida, 1993 August 31-November 16 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
      Knight File Number - 1584
      Correspondence from law firms Holland & Knight and Brouse & McDowell regarding the legal issues associated with the reincorporation of the Foundation in Florida from Ohio. Includes legal documents and IRS filings. 2 folders.
    - Knight Commission on Inter-Collegiate Athletics, 1993 October 12-29 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 1604
      Correspondence with Rev. Jesse Jackson re: National Rainbow Coalition and the Knight Commission on Inter-Collegiate Athletics.
    - Journalism Education, 1993 November 16-1995 January 27 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 1586
      Correspondence and meeting materials regarding journalism education, including mid-career education, and focus groups to study journalism education.
    - National Community Development Initiative II (NCDI II), 1993 January 26-August 3 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 1592
      Correspondence and progress report of the National Community Development Initiative II (NCDI) program, round II.
    - National Community Development Initiative (NCDI), 1993 April 29 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 1593
      Letter re: Knight Foundation's commitment to the National Community Development Initiative (NCDI) program in Miami, Philadelphia and St. Paul.
    - National Community Development Initiative (NCDI), 1994 March 21 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 1011
      National Community Development Initiative (NCDI) follow-up report to the NCDI press conference, 3/21/94. Includes a summary of press coverage, press clippings, press materials, and a press attendance list.
    - National Community Development Initiative (NCDI), 1994 June 3-October 28 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 1012
      National Community Development Initiative (NCDI). Corrrespondence to the NCDI Consortium from Bart Harvey and Paul Grogan regarding an NCDI communications plan, 1994.
    - James L. Knight Memorial, University of Miami, 1994 August 12-1995 March 28 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      Knight File Number - 1549
      Correspondence regarding a proposal by the University of Miami to create a memorial to James L. Knight, and Knight Foundation's decision not to fund it. 1994-1995.
    - Minority Journalism Handbook, 1994 August 10-November 30 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Knight File Number - 1550
      Correspondence regarding an agreement to hire an author to write a Minority Journalism Handbook, and comments on the drafts, 1994.
    - Education Program, 1994 May 11 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Knight File Number - 1594
      Letter to Walter Annenberg re: IMPACT II: The Teacher's Network, Teach for America and Teach!, programs supported by the Knight Foundation Education Program.
    - American Society of Newspaper Editors (ASNE), 1994 June 13 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      Knight File Number - 1595
      Letter regarding the publication of American Society of Newspaper Editors (ASNE) proceedings and a Knight Foundation grant.
    - Knight Chair at Duke University, 1994 August 5 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      Knight File Number - 1596
      Memo from Creed Black to Del Brinkman re: splitting the Knight Chair at Duke University between two occupants.
    - Knight-Bagehot Program at Columbia University, 1994 July 14-November 21 (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
      Knight File Number - 1607
      Meeting materials, program background and reports on the Knight-Bagehot Program at Columbia University, 1994.
    - Mel Fisher Maritime Museum, 1994 April 19 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      Knight File Number - 1837
      C. Black's correspondence with Gene Miller (Miami Herald) re. project. File incudes P. McPhee's evaluation of project.
    - Symphony Orchestra Initiative, "Magic of Music" Round I Proposals, 1994 October 31 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      Knight File Number - 1014
      Symphony Orchestra Initiative, "Magic of Music" round one proposals. Includes list of advisory committee members, a mission statement, general program, issues, proposals, and votes on proposals, 10/94.
    - Magic of Music, 1995 January 3-1998 January 6 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 1560
      Correspondence regarding the Magic of Music and use of the name for the initiative.
    - Strategic Planning, 1995 January 17-September 11 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 1562
      Correspondence with Arthur Raybin & Associates and the Knight Foundation staff re: evaluating the Foundation's progress since the last strategic plan was created. 1995.
    - Program Related Investments (PRIs), 1995 February 17-1996 February 22 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 1564
      Correspondence re: Knight Foundation's use of Program Related Investments (PRIs), discussions with staff and Brody & Weiser firm. 1995-1995.
    - Foundation for New Era Philanthropy, 1995 May 19-June 29 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 1566
      Correspondence regarding the bankruptcy of the Foundation for New Era Philanthropy and its effect on Knight Foundation grantees (Detroit Institute of Arts, Franklin Institute, and National Museum of American Jewish History), 1995.
    - Trustees--Henry King Stanford, 1996 October 18-1997 February 26 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 1579
      Documents about the retirement of Henry King Stanford as a member of the board of trustees, and a resolution honoring his service to the Foundation.
    - Archive and History Project, 1996 January 26-1998 July 31 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 1580
      Documents about the planning of the Knight Foundation Archive and written history project (by Jenny Henke) including memos detailing the progress of the projects. Includes the purpose of starting the KF archive, and an overview of the project upon completion.
    - Oral History Project, 1996 May 10-1997 June 20 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 1581
      Correspondence with consultants from the Winthrop Group about the planning and process of conducting oral history interviews with key Knight Foundation figures.
    - Winthrop Group (archives consultants), 1996 June 1 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 1582
      Proposal from The Winthrop Group, Inc., archives consultants: "Documenting the Past, Preparing for the Future: Archives and Records Management at the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation."
    - Literacy Program, 1996 September 26 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 1583
      Memo from Jim Spaniolo outlining the history of KF's national literacy grants from the Community Initiatives National Fund, 9/26/1996.
    - Journalism Program, 1997 July 30-August 1 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 1013
      "Unpunished Crimes Against Journalists" conference programs and booklets. This conference was sponsored by the Inter-American Press Association, and Creed Black attended the event in Guatemala, which was funded by KF.
    - Hamilton, Rabinowitz & Alschuler Study, 1995 August 2-1997 January 3 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 1585
      Correspondence and reports of the study of Knight Foundation's structure, staffing and operations by Hamilton, Rabinowitz & Alschuler.
    - Reimbursement and Travel Policies, 1995 February-March (Box 5, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 1588
      Memo from Creed Black re: travel and business expenses and reimbursement policies.
    - Compensation Program, 1995 September 14 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 1589
      Background report from Tim Crowe on the foundation's compensation program.
    - Expense Review Committee, 1995 June 19-September 20 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 1590
      Report of the Expense Review Committee, 6/19 and 9/20/1995.
    - Boulder Daily Camera, 1997 September 25 (Box 5, Folder 15)